Robert Silverberg

They Hide, We Seek

NOBODY HAD ANY GREAT INTEREST IN ALTERING the long-established galactic balance of power, least of all Captain Hayn Wing-Marra of the Achilles. But one thing does lead to another, and immense consequences have a way sometimes of hinging on very small pivots. In this case, the pivot was nothing more than the fact that Captain Wing-Marra, who was eleven cycles old, had spent one lifetime as an organic chemist and another as an archaeologist before he had gone to space.

It was the passion for organic chemistry, still alive in him after all those years, that had brought his Erthuma registry starship and its crew of nine, seven Erthurnoi and two Naxians, to the vicinity of the gaseous nebula W49. What they had set out to do was to explore a large molecular cloud, a spacegoing soup of complex hydrocarbons, which was certainly of scientific interest and probably had some economic value as well.

What they found nearby, hidden on the far side of the cloud, was a main-sequence star, which had four or five planets, most of which had moons. That was unexpected but not particularly surprising. The galaxy is full of stars, hundreds of millions of them, and nearly all of them have planets.

At first glance neither the star nor its planets nor any of the moons seemed particularly out of the ordinary, either, though one of the planets was close enough to Earth-type to be of potential use to Erdiurnoi. There are, however, plenty of worlds like that.

But a second glance revealed that a Locrian ship was already present in the unknown star system. It was parked in orbit around the second planet, and Locrian scouting parties were apparently at work both on the planet and its moon. That didn't make a great deal of sense, because the second planet was the Earth-type one, with a dense oxygennitrogen atmosphere very low in neon and other noble gases. Locrians are not at all comfortable in places like that. Nor would the airless moon be any more inviting to them.

So it seemed appropriate for Captain Wing-Marra to take a third and rather less casual glance. Which he did; and after that nothing would ever be quite the same for any of the six races of the galaxy that were capable of interstellar travel.

Until the discovery that a Locrian exploration force was working the same territory he was, the molecular cloud-nearly thirty light-years across and laden with marvels-had seemed quite interesting enough for Captain Wing-Marra.

"Do you see?" he said to Jorin Murry-Balff, who was his Communications.

"Not just piddling little hydroxyls and ammonias. That's cyano-octa-tetrayne there- HB9N. Eleven-atom chains, Murry-Balff! And there! That's methanol, by all the stars! CH30H!" Wing-Marra reached toward the spectrometer's dazzling screen, shining with swirls of amber and topaz and carnelian and amethyst, and tapped this brilliant swirl and that one.

"And this-and this-"

Murry-Balff didn't seem impressed. "Doesn't every molecular cloud have stuff like that in it?"

"Not this intricate, most of them. Those are very big molecules out there. Formaldehyde-112CO- Vinyl cyanide-H2CCHCN. "

"Formaldehyde? Cyanide? Sounds pretty deadly to me.

"Don't be an idiot. Those are the chemicals of life, man! " Wing-Marra leaned close, staring into the screen. Information moved in dizzying whorls before him. The spectrometer, whipping its scan-beam tirelessly across the vastness of the molecular cloud, provided color-analog displays of each organic compound it detected, reports on mass configuration, a three-dimensional distribution arc, and an assortment of other quantifiable factors. "Look, there's formic acid. And five or six amino acids, or I miss my guess. You and I and the snakes downstairs and everything else that breathes and metabolizes are built out of that stuff. And for all we know, we're alive at this moment only because wandering clouds like this seeded the newbom planets they encountered with just this sort of organic material. "

Murry-Balff shrugged. "I'll take your word for it, Captain. Chemistry was never my field. Cosmology neither." A red glow blossomed on his wristband.

"If you'll excuse me, sir-there's data coming in now from our planetary probes-"

"Dismissed," Wing-Marra murmured.

It was embarrassing for him to see the speed with which Murry-Balff, who ordinarily was in no rush, left the observation deck. Perhaps I was too ebullient for him just now, Wing-Marra thought. Or too intemperate. Certainly I was running off at the mouth a little about those molecules. He wondered whether an apology was in order. They were old friends, after all. Murry-Balff and Wing-Marra were natives of the same Erthuma world, Hesperia in the St. Dominic's Star system. The other five Erthumoi - on board came from five different worlds, none within a hundred light-years of any other; that fact alone gave the two Hesperians a certain sense of fellowship that went beyond the pseudomilitary shipboard formalities. On the other hand, Wing-Marra thought, it's Murry-Bafff s problem, not mine, if the contents of that molecular cloud don't interest him. The cloud is what we came here to investigate. Before we're through with it he'll have had to learn the formulas for a hundred different hydrocarbons, like it or not.

Wing-Marra peered at the spectrometer screen once again, and within moments he was lost in wonder.

His capacity for wonder-exultant, transcendent intellectual excitement-was one of the many contradictions out of which he was constructed. Wing-Marra was quiet and self-contained, a tall, pale, ascetic-looking man who believed in setting limits and abiding by them. To some that seemed odd and even quaint, considering that he had spent the last three cycles of his long life roaming the virtually limitless reaches of the galaxy. Wing-Marra himself saw no inconsistency in that. The way to cope with the crushing weight of infinity, he thought, was to behave as though one were capable of setting boundaries to it.

And though he seemed in many ways a passionless man, his fascination with the intricacy of the organic molecules was intense to the point of obsessiveness.

Six cycles back-his life now had encompassed eleven all told, a span of nearly a thousand Erthuma year"e had been struck suddenly by a waking vision, a startling hallucinatory display. He was living then on the sultry world called Atatakai, where the air seemed as thick as fur. Suddenly in the red evening sky he saw inexplicable pulsing points of light, which cavorted and leaped about in a wild whirling dance.

As he watched, astounded, he saw two of the shimmering light sources come together to form a pair, and then a third and larger one seize them both, and then even more complicated unions take form. And all the while the giddy dance went on. The whirling lights were strung like serpents across the sky. He had never seen anything so awesome. The patterns of their sinuous movements were elegant, compelling, sublimely beautiful. It was a revelation. It seemed to him that he was looking right into the heart of the universe, into the deepest secrets of creation.

Then, to his even greater amazement, one serpent seized its own tail in its mouth, and, ringlike now, began a fierce gyration so imperious that he fell to his knees before it, stunned and shaken. There was a powerful truth in that furiously whirling serpentine fonn-the truth of what, he had not the vaguest idea-and under the impact of that vision of the innerness of all things he trembled like a leaf in a storm. After a time he could no longer bear to watch. He closed his eyes; and when he opened them again he beheld only the cloud-choked crimson sky of Atatakai.

But the memory of the bewildering, overwhelming vision would not leave Wing-Marra's mind; and in the end he had had to seek help in regaining his mental balance. A zigzag trail through a variety of therapists and therapies brought him at last to a flat-faced dome of silvery metal that listened to him for a time and said finally in a brusque impersonal voice, "Your hallucination is not original. You are not the first to experience it. "

Wing-Marra felt as though the autoshrink had spat in his eye.

"Not-original? What the hell do you mean?"

"Another has had this vision before you, in early times, in the very distant past. It is the dream of Kekule. This is true. I have consulted the archives."

"Kekule?"

"You are a chemist. This is true."

"Why-no," said Wing-Marra, puzzled. "Not true. Not at all."

"Then you have studied chemistry," said the machine, sounding a little irritated. "This is true."

Wing-Marra thought. "I suppose so, yes. Long ago. In my first cycle, when I was at the university. But-

"A datum buried since your student days has surfaced in you. You have recapitulated the dream of Kekule," the machine told him again. "Such things happen. It is not a sign of serious mental disturbance. This is true."

"Kekule, " Wing-Marra said wonderingly. "Who's that?"

There was the momentary hum of data-search. "Friedrich August Kekule.

Erthuma of the Earthborn. Professor of chemistry at Ghent and later at

Bonn."

"Where?"

"Ancient Earth places. Do not pursue irrelevances. Kekule, pondering questions of molecular structure, saw atoms dancing before his eyes, forming a chain. Later he dreamed again and perceived the pattern of the benzene ring. This is true. The episode is well-known."

"To chemists, maybe,",said Wing-Marra. "I'm not a chemist." He felt disgruntled and obscurely let down at having paid good money to discover that the vision that had so irradiated his consciousness was a second-hand one. On the other hand, he told himself, probably it was better to hear that a phantom memory had come floating up out of some lecture of his student days than to be informed that he was going out of his mind. Still, he was in a sour mood as he left the autoshrink's cubicle.

His annoyance passed, though, and his fascination with the images that had so spontaneously leaped from the recesses of his brain remained and even deepened. He looked up Kekule and his work. Nineteenth century-my God, practically prehistoric! The dawn of science! A forgotten man, but for one great accomplishment, the theory of organic molecular structure. Kekule had demonstrated the tendency of carbon atoms to link together and to snare other atoms in their quadrivalent embrace.

And so that vision, second-hand or not, led Wing-Marra from one thing to another and another, forging ever deeper throughout all the years that remained to him in that lifetime into the study of organic chemistry. It was his hope to recapture some of the splendor and wonder of those dancing lights in the sky. It was his hope to know again that sense of being in contact with inarguable truth. His head was aswini with isomers and polymers, with alkanes and olefins, with aromatics and heterocyclics and aliphatics, with esters, ethers, aldehydes, ketones. The crisp symmetries of their bonding patterns offered him ineffable joy and held him in an ineluctable grip. And here he was, five lifetimes later, still pursuing the mysteries of the carbon compounds out here in this remote arm of the galaxy, forty thousand light-years from the home world of all Erthumoi and even farther from the planet of his own birth.

Now, throat dry, eyes wide and scarcely flickering, Wing-Marra gripped the handles of the spectrometer screen and guided its scanner this way and that across the face of the great molecular cloud. Radiant bands of colored light leaped out at him from the smoky vastness. He was staring into the miraculous core of creation.

Stars were being bom in that dense black pit. Future worlds were coalescing. The unimaginable life-forms of a billion years hence would be assembled from those rich whorls of molecular soup.

Wing-Marra felt his spirit soaring, felt his soul expanding, going forth into the cloud, walking among the drifting wonders. It was an almost godlike sensation.

"Sir?"

Murry-Balff. The intrusion was maddening, painful.

Scowling, Wing-Marra made an impatient gesture without turning away from the screen. Whatever Murry-Balff wanted, it could wait.

"Sir, this is important."

"So is this. I'm scanning the cloud."

"And we've been scanning this nearby solar system, sir. The planetary probes have pulled in something very strange. Seems that we have company."

Wing-Marra spun around swiftly.

"Company?"

"Let me show you," Murry-Balff said. He touched his wrist-plate to a wall terminal. Instantly a data screen came to life across the room. It showed a green planetary ball. Another, somewhat smaller ball, bleak and lifeless looking, orbited it at an inclination of about sixty degrees.

"This is the second planet of the system," said MurryBalff. "And its moon. I call your attention to the right side of the screen, near the planetary equator. "

Wing-Marra thought he could see a dark speck.

Murry-Balff fingered his wrist-plate. The screen zoomed into enlargement mode. Now the green world filled nearly all of the picture. Something like a black spider hung beside it. Murry-Balff made another tuning adjustment, and the spider occupied the center of the screen.

It wasn't a spider. It looked more like some narrowwaisted wasp now: three dark, gleaming elongated cylinders, linked by narrow communication tubes. Six fragile leglike appendages trailed from the hindmost cylinder. At the other end were two faceted domes, rising like huge insect eyes from the front. Spiral rows of hexagonal ports wound across each cylinder's sides.

The thing was a starship. And not of Erthuma design.

"Locrians," Murry-Balff said quietly.

"So I see." Wing-Marra pressed his fists together until his knuckles cracked, and swore. Murry-Balff brought the magnification up to the next level. It was pretty grainy, but at this level Wing-Marra thought he could actually make out the insectlike figures of the aliens moving about behind the ports. He shook his head. "What in God's name would Locrians be doing here?"

The crew assembled fast, all but the Naxians, who needed more time. Snakes always needed more time, no matter what. Wing-Marra didn't feel like waiting for them. He kept the data screen lit and ordered Murry-Balff to maintain real-time tracking surveillance of the Locrian ship.

"We're under no obligation to withdraw," Wing-Marra said. "This is unclaimed territory and remains that way until they've established valid possession. Simply being the first to get here doesn't constitute valid possession. "

"They aren't under any obligation to withdraw either," Linga Hyath, his Cosmography, pointed out.

"Understood."

"T'hey might not agree that they don't have valid possession," said his Diplomacy, Ayana Sanoclaro. Hyath and Sanoclaro looked at each other and exchanged quick, smug nods of satisfaction. Wing-Marra could usually count on them to think the same way and to express essentially the same ideas at approximately the same time.

They were both wiry, long-limbed women with the gaunt, attenuated look that natives of low-gravity worlds generally have, and they appeared to be not merely sisters but twins: the same pale blue eyes, the same immense cas- cades of golden hair, the same thin, pinched features. The odd thing was that they were not at all related, but came, in fact, from worlds a thousand light-years apart. Some genotypes are strikingly persistent. Wing-Marra said, "Are you suggesting that they might make trouble for us?"

"They might have serious objections to our hanging around here," Sanoclaro said.

"If they think there's something really worthwhile here, they might defend their claim in a way we wouldn't like," said Hyath.

Mikoil Karpov, the Biochemistry, said, "You imply that they'd take hostile action?"

"They might," said Sanoclaro.

Karpov blinked. He was a squat, broad-shouldered man, heavy jowled, densely bearded, from the chilly world of Zima, and his Erthumat was thickened by strong Russkiye inflections. "You are talking about acts of war? And you are actually serious? The idea's absurd. Nobody makes war."

"Erthumoi used to, not all that long ago."

Karpov gestured emphatically. "It was plenty long ago. Nobody fires on peaceful ships."

"Especially across species lines," said the Navigation, a dark, soft, tiny, deceptively feminine-looking woman named Eslane Ree, who came from Doppler IV. "The Locrians can see that this is an Erthuma ship. Maybe the Crotonites still like to squabble among themselves, or, from what I hear from our two, the Naxians. But those are Locrians over there. They don't even have a history of intraspecies warfare-why would they take a shot at us? I'm with Karpov here. We're spinning horrors out of nothing at all."

"Maybe so. But what are Locrians doing here, though?" Linga Hyath asked.

"Locrians don't ordinarily go sniffing around high-oxygen worlds. And from the looks of it, this one is particularly badly suited for them. Six gulps of that atmosphere and they'd be drunk for a month. They must have seen something out of the usual here that got their attention in a big way."

"Who says?" Eslane Ree demanded. "Have we?"

Hyath shrugged. "We've only just arrived."

"Perhaps so have they."

"But they'd have taken one look and moved on, since this world is plainly useless to them," said Ayana Sanoclaro. "Unless they've spotted something. And if they have, my guess is that they'll go to great lengths, maybe to surprisingly great lengths, to keep us away from it."

Eslane Ree gave the elongated blond woman a sour glare. "Paranoia! Hyperdefensiveness!"

"Foresight," Sanoclaro retorted. "Prudence."

"What are you advocating?" asked the Maintenance, Septen Bolangyr, who came from a high-ultraviolet world in the Nestor Cluster and whose skin, artificially hyped with melanin, was a lustrous purple green. "Should I activate the defensive screens, sir? Do you want me to get the cannons ready? If we are to go on a war footing, Captain, then tell me so right now. But I want the order in writing, and I want it with a date and a seal. "

"Stay easy," Wing-Marra said. "We're a long way from fighting any space battles. What I'm going to do is contact these Locrians and find out whether we have a problem with them. But I hope you'll go along with my feeling that we ought to take a firm position about staying here, regardless of what they say."

"Even if they threaten us?" Hyath asked.

"They won't," said Karpov. Eslane Ree nodded in vigorous agreement.

"If they do?" Wing-Marra asked.

Eslane Ree said, "It would depend on the nature of the threat. We'd be foolish to stay here if they're willing to blow us out of he sky."

"Locrians?" Karpov said incredulously.

"Sufficient greed can turn any species warlike," Ayana Sanoclaro said, looking to her friend Hyath for support. "Even Locrians. The fact that the Six Races have avoided serious conflict with each other up till now is irrelevant. The evolutionary imperatives that have carried all six species this far have plenty of aggression buried in them, and the right motivation surely can bring that aggression to life. 'Locrians or no, if what they've found here is so valuable that-"

"We don't know that they've found anything, and-

"How can we assume--

"The unmotivated adolescent belligerence of these arguments is utterly-"

"The nalvete of-"

"More than fifteen hundred years of peaceful space exploration behind us and we still regard ourselves as capable of reverting to the level of-"

"Not us, them!"

"Us too! Who began this whole-"

"Enough!" Wing-Marra said sharply. "Sanoclaro, tell those two snakes of ours-excuse me, those two Naxians-to get themselves on deck without any further delay. Brief them on what's going on. Murry-Balff, I want to be talking to those Locrians in five minutes or less. Bolangyr, work up an inventory of our battle stores, just for the hell of it, but don't activate anything, you hear, not a thing. The rest of you stand by and hold your peace, will you?" He glowered at the spectrometer screen, where clumps of gorgeous amide radicals and polyhydric alcohols were circling in a stately sarabande of astonishing colors. Whatever the Locrians were doing here, he thought, it ought to be possible to work out some kind of territorial agreement with them in half an hour or so, and then he would be able to get down to his real work. We are all rational beings. Reason will prevail. We of the Six Races have all managed to coexist in interstellar space for a very long time without any serious conflicts of interest. Why start now? Why, indeed?

The Locrian gave its name as Speaker-to-Erthumoi. Murry-Balff had asked to talk to Ship-Commander, but Speaker-to-Erthumoi was the best he was able to get. Of course, they might be the same person, Wing-Marra knew. Locrians change their names as often as they change functions. Perhaps it was not even legitimate to regard Locrian "nanies" as names.

He put the transmission into image-stasis, freezing the communication channel. The Locrian would simply have to sit there on hold until the Erthuma captain had a clearer idea of the situation. Turning to one of his Naxians, Wing-Marra said, "Is this meant as an insult, Blue Sphere? Should I insist on speaking to Ship-Commander?"

The Naxian studied the motionless image of the Locrian that glittered from the frozen screen for a long while, assessing the information visible to it-her on the insectoid creature's seemingly impassive face. It is the extraordinary gift of Naxians to be able to read the emotional outputnot the minds, only the emotions-of any life-form, no matter how alien to it. Greed, anger, lust, shame, compassion, whatever: All creatures are open books to Naxians. Even when all they have to work with is a static image on a screen. How they did it, no Erthuma knew. The various stargoing species of the galaxy had many sorts of intuitive powers that were difficult for Erthumoi to comprehend.

The Naxian seemed to be working hard, though. Meditative ripples and quivers ran the length of its-her pink, narrow snakelike body. So intense was Blue Sphere's concentration that it-she went into flipper mode for a few moments, extruding stubby fringed grasping organs from its-her otherwise limbless form, then absorbing them again.

"You may proceed, Captain," Blue Sphere announced after a time. "The Locrians intend no insult. Mere efficiency of communication is the most likely purpose. I suspect Ship-Commander is less fluent in Erthurnat than this one. At any rate the Locrian's emotional aura is benign."

"But apprehensive," offered the other Naxian, Rosy Tetrahedron. "Definite anxiety is evident. The Locrian feels strong uncertainty as to Erthuma motivations or intentions in this sector of space. "

"Fine," Wing-Marra said. "If they're as nervous about us as we are about them, there's hope for working something out. Reciprocity is the mother of security, eh, Sanoclaro? Eh? Old diplomatic proverb."

Sanoclaro didn't smile. But he hadn't really expected her to.

He killed the image-stasis and the screen came to life again. The Locrian could have walked away from the transmitter while Wing-Marra's colloquy with the Naxians was going on, but it was still there. At least Wing-Marra assumed that it was the same one. He stared at it. What he saw was a fleshless angular head much longer than it was wide, a lipless V-shaped beak of a mouth, a single giant glaring eye shielded by a clear bubblelike plate hinged at each side, a thin tubular neck sprouting out of a flimsy, skeletal six-limbed trunk.

'Me Locrian looked for all the world like a giant insect, a dry parched chitinous thing that would probably crunch if you hit it with the edge of your hand. Very likely they had evolved from some kind of low-phylum insectlike arthropods on their dry, chilly home world, which belonged to an orange K5 sun in the- Cygnus arm of the galaxy. But there was nothing low-phylum about them now. They were chordate vertebrates with tough siliceous spinal columns to support their scaly gray green exoskeletons. And they had tough, shrewd brains in their narrow, elongated skulls.

The moment the stasis broke the Locrian said, "We request clarification, Erthuma representative. Do we speak with Diplomacy or Administration?"

"Administration. I am Hayn Wing-Marra, captain, Erthuma of Hesperia in St. Dominic's Star system."

The Locrian made a crackling sound that seemed like displeasure. "We request Diplomacy. It is a point of protocol. Transspecies discussions are protocol matters."

Wing-Marra felt like screaming. The last thing he wanted was to have to conduct this discussion by way of Ayana Sanoclaro, considering the wild suspicions she had just been voicing. But the Locrian was right: Contact across species lines in open space had to follow protocol. Reluctantly Wing-Marra beckoned to Sanoclaro, who gave him a little smirk of triumph and stepped into the pale yellow glow of the communications field.

"What we want to know, Speaker-to-Erthumoi," she said without preamble, "is whether you're staking a claim to the solar system that lies adjacent to our present position. "

"Negative," said the Locrian immediately. Though the two ships were eighty-eight million kilometers apart at that moment, the communications field-a modulated-neutrino carrier wave operating through hyperspace-permitted instantaneous communication between them. For that matter, it would have permitted communication at essentially the same response time even if the ships had been at opposite ends of the galaxy. "No claim to this system has been recorded."

Wing-Marra held up both his hands. Making two circles out of his thumbs and forefingers, he moved them in an elaborate pantomime that he hoped would suggest the orbital relationship of the second planet and its huge moon. But Sanoclaro, without even looking at him, had aheady begun to ask the obvious next question.

"Are you claiming just the second planet, then? Or its moon?"

"Is there Erthuma interest in the second planet?" the Locrian countered.

The Naxian who called it-herself Blue Sphere moved outside the field's scanner range and signaled to WingMarra that it was picking up increased ambiguities and uncertainties. Wing-Marra, peering at the screen, sought to detect some change in the Locrian's expression, but Speakerto-Fxthumoi's rigid features showed not a flicker of movement. An integument that chitinous wasn't capable of much movement, or perhaps of any at all. Whatever clues the Naxians used in doing their little trick, facial expressions didn't seem to play an important role.

Sanoclaro looked to Wing-MarTa for a cue. He indicated the spectrometer screen, ablaze with drifting hydrocarbon masses.

"We are purely a scientific mission," Sanoclaro told the Locrian. "We're here to study the molecular cloud. We have no territorial intentions whatsoever. "

"Nor do we," said Speaker-to-Erthumoi. "We require only unhindered completion of our research. "

Wing-Marra frowned. He was beginning to wonder if any of this was any business of his at all. If the only thing the Locrians wanted was to be left alone to snoop around the second world, and all that he wanted was to be left alone to study the molecular cloud-

No. The directives were very clear. When an Fxthuma ship encountered a ship belonging to any of the other five races in open space, the Erthuma vessel, regardless of its own purpose, was required to file a report on the activities of the other spacecraft. Even though no one saw any serious risk of anything so farfetched and implausible as interstellar warfare breaking out, it behooved the Erthurnoi as the youngest and least experienced of the six starfaring peoples-to keep close watch on everything that their rivals might be up to. Assuming that their activities would never be anything but benign, regardless of the generally peaceful relationships that had prevailed among the Six Races since the first Erthuma entry into interstellar space, was folly.

He needed more information.

Making the planet-and-moon gesture again, Wing-Marra tried to depict the orbiting Locrian ship by moving his nose in a circle around the equator of the finger and thumb that represented the planet. Sanoclaro shot him a mystified look. Abandoning the pantomime, Wing-Marra whispered angrily, "Try to find out what the hell they're doing here, will you?"

Sanoclaro said, "May we inquire into the nature of your mission?"

Blue Sphere, still out of scanner range, signaled that increased agitation was coming from the Locrian. Or so Wing-Marra thought the Naxian was trying to tell him.

It was maddening for the captain to have to deal through this many intermediaries. Every ship carried a Diplomacy as a matter of course, but Wing-MarTa hadn't expected to need to make use of Sanoclaro's services in this remote region. And the Naxians, though they were valuable interpreters of nonverbal messages in tricky situations like this one, weren't always easy for non-Naxians to understand.

Speaker-to-Erthumoi said after a long pause, "Our mission is exploratory also."

Wing-Marra pantomimed drunkenness.

Sanoclaro looked puzzled again. Then, smiling to show that she understood, she said, "But surely a high-oxygen world such as the one nearby can be of little practical use to Lociians. "

Speaker-to-Erthumoi was silent.

"May we inquire whether the nature of your exploration is exploratory?"

Sanoclaro said. "Or is there perhaps some other purpose?"

"Other," said the Locrian.

"Other than scientific?"

"Other, yes. "

"Is its nature such that our presence here will disrupt your work?"

"Not necessarily."

"Then it is proper to conclude that the representative of the Galactic Sphere of Locria has no objection to our continuing to remain in this region?"

Another long silence.

"No objection," Speaker-to-Erthumoi replied finally.

Both Naxians now signaled that they were picking up distress, resentment, suspicion, general contradiction of spoken statement.

Wing-MarTa fumed. He hoped Sanoclaro didn't think that having obtained the Locrians' permission for them to stay here was any sort of wonderful achievement. This was, after all, open territory.

He said under his breath, "I need to know what they're up to!"

Sanoclaro said, "Our captain instructs me to obtain data from you concerning the nature of your mission."

"I will reply shortly," said Speaker-to-Erdiumoi. There was yet another lengthy pause. Then the image froze. This time it was the Locrians who had imposed the stasis, no doubt so Speaker-to-Erthumoi could engage in a quick off-screen strategy session with Ship-Commander.

Wing-Marra said to Sanoclaro, "If it's just a routine mapping mission, they shouldn't be as edgy as the Naxians say they are. When they come back on, see if you can pin them down about their reasons for landing scouts on that planet and its moon."

"What do you think I'm trying to do?"

"What I think," said Linga Hyath, "is that they probably were just on a routine mapping mission, but they found something on the second world or its moon that was way out of the ordinary, and so they're sticking around to take a close look at it, and they wish we'd get the hell out of here before we find it too."

"Ilank you," Wing-Marra told the Cosmography. "Your grasp of the obvious is extraordinarily profound."

Hyath glared and began to reply.

"Save it," said Wing-Marra. The screen was alive again.

Speaker-to-Erthumoi-if that indeed was who was on the screen now-looked astonishingly transformed, as though it had been wearing a mask before and now had removed it. The hard, sharp-angled gray chitin of its all but featureless face had been opened back like the two doors of a cabinet, and what was visible now was the bare surface of its great staring glassy inner eye, the immensely penetrating organ that Locrians revealed only when they needed to see with particular clarity. Facing that eye was like facing fifty Naxians at once. -It seemed to be seeing right into him. Wing-Marra felt stripped bare, down to bone and tendon. He had never seen a Locrian in full percept mode before, and he didn't like it.

To hell with it, he thought. I don't have anything to hide.

He met the glare of that terrible eye without flinching.

The Locrian said, "Ship-Commander requests face-toface contact with Erthuma-captain in order to continue the discussion in a more fruitful way. He proposes stochastic choice to determine which ship is to be the site of the meeting."

Sanoclaro looked inquiringly toward Wing-Marra, who nodded at once.

"Agreed," the Diplomacy told the alien. "Shall we flip a coin?"

"That method is acceptable."

"Do you want us to flip one?"

"We prefer to do that," said the Locrian.

Again Wing-Marra nodded. His irritation was mounting rapidly. Let them use a coin with two heads, for all he cared. What did it matter whether the meeting took place on his ship or theirs? He just wanted to get on with his work.

" Select your choice," said Speaker-to-Erthumoi. It held up its claw, revealing a shining six-edged coin of some bright coppery metal grasped between two of its numerous many-jointed fingers. One face of the coin showed some Locrian's beaky big-eyed head, and when the alien turned it over Wing-Marra saw jagged abstract patterns on the reverse.

"I'll take tails," Wing-Marra said.

"'Tails?"

"The side that doesn't have the head."

"Ah. "

Something happened off screen. Speaker-to-Erthumoi said, after a moment, "We have tossed the coin. Your selection proved to be correct. We will send a boarding party. How soon can you receive us?"

There was more grumbling, of course. Hyath and Sanoclaro, the suspicious ones, were convinced that the whole coin-tossing gambit had been nothing but a ploy to insinuate a Locrian force aboard the ship, perhaps so that they could seize it. Eslane Ree thought that was crazy, and said so. Mikoil Karpov, too, wanted to know why the two women were taking such an alarmist position. Even MurryBalff, who usually went along with anything Wing-Marra said, thought it would have been a better idea to have sent the Diplomacy over to the alien vessel to conduct the conference.

"If they're up to anything funny, better that they do it over there," Murry-Balff said. "And to her, not US."

Annoyed as he was by the paranoia of Sanoclaro and Hyath, Wing-MarTa found nothing to amuse him in his old friend's frivolity. He was a cautious man but he saw no reason for fear. The risk was all on the Locrians' side. They were the ones who would be boarding a strange ship, after all. He couldn't bring himself to believe that they had anything so wild as an armed takeover in mind. No, the coin toss had probably been honest, and the Locrians could probably be trusted. Or else they were working up something so devious that no sane person could be expected to be on guard against it.

Within the hour a beetlelike hypershuttle brought a four Locrian delegation across the gulf between the two ships.

It popped back into normal space astonishingly close to the Achilles and coasted in for a docking.

Four Locrians came scrambling through the access lock. They were taller than the tallest of Erthumoi, but so light and frail were their bodies-six pipelike limbs and hardly any thorax-that they seemed little more than walking skeletons.

By way of protection against the intoxicating richness of the Erthuma ship's atmosphere, they were wearing ftanslucent spacesuits that hung about them in loose, awkward folds, like old baggy skin. Anything beyond a 10 percent oxygen concentration was dizzying to them, and furthermore they preferred to breathe air that was thinned by a substantial neon component, which the Achilles was unable to supply.

The first thing the Locrians saw was the spherical golden grille and trembling corkscrew antennae of the simultrans machine that Murry-Balff had set up in the center of the meeting room. They obviously didn't like it.

"There is no real need to employ this device," said one of the Locrians coolly, giving the translating gadget a fiercely contemptuous stiff-necked glare. "Your language holds no mysteries for us."

Wing-Marra had expected that. The other races were always scornful of Erdiuma artificial-intelligence gadgets, because in one way or another they were able to manage most things without such mechanical assistance. The simultrans was capable of rendering real-time translations of anything said in any of the six galactic languages into any or all of the other five.

Erthumoi, notorious for their general incapacity to master the ancient and intricate languages of most alien species, found the machine extremely useful. The others didn't.

But Wing-Marra suspected there was more to the Locrian objections to the simultrans than simple racial prejudice. With the simultrans offering instantaneous translation of anything said, no members of either species would be able to speak to each other in surreptitious asides unintelligible to the other party. Wing-Marra saw that as a distinct advantage for him, since some or all of the Locrians appeared to be fluent in Erthumat, but no one aboard the Achilles understood more than a smattering of Locrian. Evidently the Locrians saw things the same way.

Smiling grandly, he said, "Ah, but we feel it is only courteous to offer you this small assistance. You are already under the stress of having come aboard a strange ship, and you are compelled to conduct this meeting clad in spacesuits that doubtless must cause you some discomfort. We would not burden you with the obligation to converse in an alien tongue as well."

"But it is not necessary that we-"

"Permit me to insist. I am overwhelmed by your unselfishness but I could not bear the shame of having inconvenienced you so deeply. "

There was a frosty silence. The Locrian looked-so far as Wing-Marra was capable of telling-extremely annoyed.

But after a moment the Locrian said, "Very well. Let us use the translator. You know me as Speaker-to-Erthumoi. I am accompanied by Ship-Commander and Recorder."

Three names, four Locrians, no indication of what was what or which was whom. Wing-Marra didn't even try to get an explanation.

"I am Captain Wing-Marra," he said. "This is my Diplomacy, Ayana Sanoclaro.

These Naxians travel with us and will observe. They call themselves Blue Sphere and Rosy Tetrahedron. Jorin Murry-Balff, my Communications, will record our conversation. With your permission, of course."

"Granted," said Speaker-to-Erthumoi.

Within the helmet of its suit its head split open, revealing the great luminous beacon of its inner eye.

Wing-Marra shivered.

One of the other Locrians opened its eye also. WingMarra could not decide whether that one was Recorder or Ship-Commander. Did it matter? Perhaps they were all Recorder. Or all four were Ship-Commander. Aliens, he thought. Go and figure.

The other two remained sealed. A safety measure, WingMarra suspected.

Locrians were terribly vulnerable when their inner eye was exposed. The slightest pressure against it-the touch of a hand -- could blind or even kill. There fore they opened their facial hinges only when they deemed it absolutely necessary to do so.

Even in normal visual mode, Wing-Marra had heard, Locrians saw three-dimensionally, penetrating into the interiors of things. With the inner eye unveiled, he imagined that they could see right into his soul. The two unveiled ones were watching him from opposite sides, as though trying to read all aspects of him. It was like being in the crossfire of two brilliant lasers. Wing-Marra understood now why they had asked for this face-to-face meeting. They wanted a chance to evaluate the nature of the Erthuma they were dealing with in a way that long distance conversation via neutrino wave could not provide.

Well, let them look, Wing-Marra thought. Let them look as long and as hard and as deep as they like.

The silent surveillance went on and on and on.

After a time he stopped finding it merely disagreeable and began to find it worrisome. He glanced toward the Naxians for an opinion. But they were calm. They lay motionless, placidly coiled side by side in a comer of the room, watching with unblinking eyes. They were in their limbless relaxation state. Evidently they saw no cause for alarm in this peculiar wordless interrogation.

At length one of the unveiled Locrians-not the one who had identified itself as Speaker-to-Erthumoi-said, "We believe that you are trustworthy-"

"I am deeply grateful for that," Wing-Marra said, trying hard not to sound sarcastic.

"These are delicate matters in which we find ourselves enmeshed," another of the Locrians intoned. "We must operate from a position of absolute assurance that you win not abuse our confidence."

"Of course," Wing-Marra said.

"Let us come to the point, Captain Wing-Marra," said the fourth alien.

"What we would prefer is that you leave this region at once, making no further investigation."

Ayana Sanoclaro uttered a muffled, undiplomatic grunt of surprise and anger. Wing-Marra's own reaction was closer to amusement. Was that why they had given him this elaborate scrutiny? That seemed a preposterous buildup for such a straightforward, almost simpleminded demand. Did they think he was a child? But he restrained himself.

Carefully he said, "We have come a great distance, and we have significant research goals that we wish to carry out. Leaving here now is out of the question for us. "

"Understood. You will not leave and we do not expect you to. As we have said, the problem we face here is delicate, and we would prefer to handle it without the complications that the intrusion of another galactic species can bring. But we state only a preference."

Wing-MarTa nodded. He had forgotten how literal minded Locrians could be.

"Aside from our going away from here right away, then, what is it you really want from us?" he asked.

The two Locrians who had not opened their inner eyes now drew back the hinges of their faces. Wing-Marra found himself confronting four great blazing orbs. Within the translucent helmets, four sharp-edged alien beaks were slowly opening and closing-a sign, he supposed, of intense concentration. But he suspected also that it might connote Locrian tension, disquietude, malaise. Something about their stance suggested that: They held themselves even more stiffly than usual, practically motionless, limbs rigid.

The Naxians too now seemed distressed, probably from having picked up jittery auras from the Locrians. They had uncoiled and lay stretched taut, side by side, their eyes gleaming and bulging, their little transient flipper-limbs shooting in and out of their sides.

"It may be the case," said one of the Locrians finally, just as the silence had begun to seem interminable, "that we are not able to deal with the problem that we see here unaided. Indeed, we are quite certain of this. What we propose, therefore, is an alliance."

"What?"

"We will recapitulate. There is a problem in this solar system that causes us much concern. We would rather conceal it from you than share it with you; but because we have come to feel that we are incapable of solving the problem without assistance, specifically without Erthuma assistance, we are willing to regard the arrival of Erthumoi at just this moment as providential. And invite you to work with us toward a solution."

Wing-Marra felt a faintly sickening sensation, as though he were teetering on the rim of an infinitely deep mine shaft. What, he wondered, was he getting into here?

He looked from one Locrian to the next, four fleshless, forbidding insectoid heads whose alien eyes blazed like frightful torches.

"All right," he said. "Tell me something about this problem of yours."

"Let us show you," said the Locrian who was Speakerto-Erthumoi.

The alien gestured to another of the Locrians-perhaps it was Recorder-who drew from the folds of its spacesuit a small brassy-looking metallic object that Wing-Marra recognized as an Locrian image-projecting device. The Locrian set it on the floor in front of itself.

"We came here," said Speaker-to-Erthumoi, "much as you did, simply to explore. We had no military or economic purpose in mind. As you already recognize, the planets of this solar system would be of little value to us. But in the course of our reconnaissance, we came upon something in the vicinity of the second world that aroused our curiosity. We investigated more closely, and this is what we observed."

Speaker-to-Erthumoi nodded. Recorder-if that was who it was-stared at the image projector until a warm golden glow, like that of a little sun, began to come from it. The device, Wing-Marra knew, was tuned to the Locrian's brain waves.

Suddenly the room blossomed into vivid color. A threedimensional scene, so immediate in its presence that it seemed almost as though the wall of the Achilles had opened to reveal another world just outside, took form before Wing-Marra's eyes.

It was another world. Heavy-bellied orange clouds hung low in a deep turquoise sky. The vantage point at which Wing-Marra found himself was just below the clouds, perhaps a kilometer above the surface. He saw dense blue-green forests below, broad rivers, a chain of huge shimmering lakes.

Far off on the horizon a smallish G-type sun was setting, streaking the air with brilliant bands of violet and gold. On the opposite side of the sky a moon had already begun rising, huge and oppressively close, perhaps no more than one hundred thousand kilometers away. Its bare, smooth, gleaming face was marked with the dark, rugged lines of what must surely be immense mountain ranges ringing shining ovals that might have been the beds of long-dry seas.

"What you see is the second world of the nearby system on a summer evening," Speaker-to-Erdiumoi announced. "It is not an agreeable place. The mean temperature at the altitude of observation is approximately 315 K. It is slightly cooler at ground level, but still unpleasantly warm, at least by our standards. The atmosphere is composed almost entirely of nitrogen and oxygen, with substantial water vapor and minor components of argon and carbon dioxide. The atmospheric pressure is equally displeasing, approximately seven times as great, at surface level, as on Locriannorm worlds. There are strong tidal effects, caused by the proximity of a satellite unusually large in relation to its primary, and a vortex of relatively cool air descending permanently from the poles creates constant strong cyclonic winds. Ordinarily we would not have continued our observations of such a planet beyond this point. However-"

The other Locrian made a barely perceptible movement. The focal intensity of the image changed, and Wing-Marra abruptly found himself looking at the second world from a point not far above the tangled canopy of a tropical jungle.

Winged creatures were moving slowly through the air.

"Native life?" Wing-Marra asked.

"No. Look again."

He narrowed his eyes against the brightness of the sky, doubly fit by the spectacular sunset and the cold white glory of the gigantic shining moon.

What had seemed to him at first quick glance to be huge birds now appeared something quite other: humanoid figures with small stubby legs and two slender arms held close against their chests. From bulging humps below their shoulders rose two powerful limblike projections heavily banded with muscle and anchored by jutting keels on their chests; and out of those came the giant fleshy wings, far larger in area than the creatures themselves, whose steady stately flapping motions held them aloft.

Then one of the flying creatures turned so that its narrow, tapering head was clearly outlined against the sky, and Wing-Marra could plainly see the great curving bony crest rising from its forehead and the equally astonishing jut of its elongated chin. He had no further doubt. Another of the galactic races had preceded both Locrians and Erthurnoi to this place.

"Crotonites?" he said, with a little involuntary shudder.

"Indeed. See, now, their base." Focus shifted once again, and Wing-Marra beheld the elaborate webwork weave of a Crotonite nest, spreading through the treetops to cover perhaps a hectare. The winged aliens, equipped with breathing masks to help them deal with an atmosphere whose chemistry was not much to their liking, moved busily back and forth, swooping down to land, disappearing within the strands of the delicate structure, emerging again and rising skyward with strong, unhurried strokes of their great wings.

"If there are Crotonites here," Wing-Marra said, "why haven't we detected any signs of a Crotonite starship in the vicinity?"

"No doubt it has been here and gone," said the Locrian. "So far as we can determine, the Crotonite base here has been established for quite some time. We regard it a semipermanent outpost."

Wing-Marra looked toward Sanoclaro. The Diplomacy's expression was solemn. She said, "It might just be a world they could use, I suppose. Thick atmosphere, warm climate. Though the atmosphere doesn't seem poisonous enough to make them really happy, but they could work out some kind of adaptation to help them cope with all that oxygen. They seem to be doing all right with those breathing masks. Well, if they've filed a claim, we'll have to apply to them for permission if we want to make a landing and set up a base. But not if we're only going to make a ship survey of the molecular cloud. This solar system lies completely outside the cloud. Their claim wouldn't give them any rights to adjacent space."

"T'hey have filed no claim," Speaker-to-Erthumoi said.

Wing-Marra frowned. "No?"

"Nothing. Nor have they made any response to our presence here. They seem to be making an elaborate point of ignoring us. It is as though they have not noticed us. Or you, we presume, since you evidently have not heard from them. They simply go about their business, setting out every day from that base and exploring the planet in an ever widening circle."

"Then I fail to see the difficulty," the Erthuma captain said. "if they don't care that others are here, why should you care so much that they are? This whole solar system's a free zone for everybody. And in any case there doesn't seem to be much here of any importance. "

"You have not heard the entire story yet," said Speaker-to-Erthumoi. "They also have a base on the moon. "

Another tiny movement by the Locrian operating the projector, and the lush tropical scene vanished in an instant. Its place was taken by something far more harsh: the barren, airless landscape of the second planet's moon. Now Wing-Marra found himself at the edge of what must have been an ancient sea.

A shallow, barren basin of some white limy rock stretched to the horizon. Colossal mountains, their lofty summits unexpectedly eroded and rounded as they might have been on a world that had an atmosphere, rose to one side. The dazzling green bulk of the second world hung close overhead, filling the sky, terrifyingly near, seemingly about to plunge down upon him.

The Crotonites had woven a seven-sided Crotonite dwelling that sprawled over the brightly lit plain just at the edge of the mountains' shadow. And Crotonites, swaddled in individual pressure-bubbles that covered them, wings and all, from crested heads to stubby legs, were driving about in land-crawlers. But their movements were incomprehensible. They seemed to be circling a big empty area a dozen or so kilometers from their base. From time to time one of the crawlers would abruptly disappear, as though it had been devoured by some unseen lurking monster, or one would wink suddenly into existence in the middle of the plain, as if popping out of nowhere.

"I don't understand," Wing-Marra said. "Where are they going? Where are they coming from?"

"We ask ourselves the same thing," said Speaker-to-Erthumoi. "Our answer is that the Crotonites believe they must go to great pains to conceal whatever they are doing on that lunar plain. And so they have generated a zone of invisibility around it. "

"Can they do such a thing?" Wing-Marra asked, surprised.

"It would appear that they can. We see nothing; and yet we feel the presence of living beings in that empty zone."

Murry-Balff said, "What do your instrument readings show? If there are Crotonites moving around out there, you'd be getting infrared output. And if they've set up some kind of invisibility gadget, there might be some measurable light-wave distortion around its edges. Or various other forms of data corruption."

"We do not have instruments capable of measuring what cannot be seen, " replied the Locrian, and there was a distinctly icy edge to its flat, unemotional voice. "What we detect is the emanations of intelligent beings, radiating in the Crotonite mind-spectrum, coming from a place that seems to be uninhabited and uninhabitable. "

Wing-Marra said, "What do you think they're trying to hide? A weapons factory? A center for espionage activities? A laboratory for secret scientific research?"

"We have considered all those possibilities. They have varing orders of probability. But what we think is most probable of all is that they have discovered something of great value on that moon, and do not want any other galactic race to know what they have."

"That might explain why they haven't filed a claim to this system," Sanoclaro said. "Even though their occupation of the planet and the moon would ordinarily validate any claim. Maybe they didn't want to call this place to anybody's attention even to the extent of claiming it. They gambled instead that nobody else would find it."

"This is our belief also," said the Locrian.

Sanoclaro shook her head. "Bad luck for them that not one but two different galactic races stumbled on it right after them, against all odds. But sometimes it does happen that the needle in the haystack gets found."

Speaker-to-Erdiumoi said, "What it is the Crotonites have discovered here, we have no idea, any more than we know how they are able to conceal it. But Crotonites would not remain in so hostile an environment without strong motivation. We wish to know what that motivation is: that is, what it is that they are concealing."

Wing-Marra laughed. "We thought you were the ones who had found something valuable here."

"What we found was Crotonites working here secretly in a zone of mystery. We wish to know what that zone of mystery contains. And so we invite you to enter into partnership with us. "

"So you've already told us. But just what kind of partnership do you mean?"

"We have one asset to offer: the discovery that the Crotonites are hiding something. But we are unable to proceed beyond that. You Fxthumoi can provide, perhaps, the asset we lack: the technology by which the Crotonites' shield of concealment can be penetrated. Let us work together to expose and exploit their secret. And we will share, half and half, in such profits as come from the venture. "

"Half and half?" Wing-Marra said. "If there's something valuable on that moon, don't you think the Crotonites are entitled to a share, too? Or are you planning to cut them out of it altogether?"

"To be sure," said Speaker-to-Erthumoi. "We may have to divide the profits in thirds."

The discussion aboard the Achilles that followed the departure of the Locrian boarding party was very possibly the loudest and most vociferous that Wing-Marra had ever known in all the eleven cycles of his life.

Sanoclaro, of course, was horrified at the notion of entering into any kind of deal with Locrians, and urged Wing-Marra to head for the nearest Erthurna world at once and turn the affair over to the authorities there.

But her friend Linga Hyath, to everyone's amazement, disagreed completely with her: She was all for finding out without any delay what it was that the -Crotonites were hiding onthe second planet's moon. If the cool and unemotional Locrians were so churned up over it, she said, then it was important to know what they had. Mikoil Karpov took the same position, and so did Murry-Balff, who was already bubbling with notions of how to break through the Crotonite data screen.

Eslane Ree, though, was on Sanoclaro's side. "This is simply none of our business," the Navigation said quietly, and when Hyath and Murry-Balff took issue with her, she said it again less quietly, and then very loudly indeed. For a small woman she was capable of astonishing ferocity when she thought the occasion warranted it, and apparently she thought this one did. "We're here to do scientific research. Not to strike bargains with aliens."

"You look on aliens as enemies?" Karpov asked.

"I don't look on them as friends," Eslane Ree shot back. "They tolerate us in the galaxy because they have no choice. We came muscling into a system that they had carved up into five nice slices while we were still using stone axes, and demanded our piece of it. Well, because interstellar war is currently obsolete, and the galaxy is so big that even the Five Races hadn't had time to explore it all, they graciously allowed us to become the Sixth Race. But they don't trust us and they don't like us, and they all think they're a whole lot wiser than we are, and maybe they are. We haven't been out in the galaxy long enough to know. "

"We have achieved so much in such a very short time," said Karpov ponderously. "Is that not-"

Eslane Ree glared at him.

"In a short time, yes, we've figured out black holes and pulsars and hyperdrives and neutrino-wave communication, and maybe all that makes us think we're pretty hot stuff. But when it comes to galactic politics we're still strictly novices. If the Locrians want to do something dirty to the Crotonites, let diem. Why should we risk getting drawn in? Because the Locrians tell us they'll cut us in on the profits? W/un profits? When have the bugs ever gone out of their way to cut us in on anything? How do we know what they're really up to? What they want to do is use us. And when they're through using us, they might very well get rid of us, if it turns out what we've stumbled across is something that's inconvenient for us to know."

"Madness," Karpov muttered.

"I don't think you have any right-"

"Please," said Septen Bolangyr. "It is my turn to speak."

Bolangyr, who usually was indifferent to discussions of policy, also argued in favor of keeping out of potential trouble. "We don't understand much about Locrian psychology and we don't even begin to understand the Crotonites," he argued. "All we know, really, is that both of them are older and probably shrewder races than ours, and that, as Eslane Ree says, neither of them have much respect or liking for us. Eslane Roe is correct. We're likely to find ourselves way over our heads if we get mixed up in some squabble between them."

"Wrong!" Karpov cried. "Such a great opportunity to learn! We must not turn our backs' Not only the mystery of this moon, but the mystery of Locrians, the mystery of Crotonites! Go among them, is what we must do! Engage them! Entangle ourselves! How else can we learn? How can we simply turn our backs at such a time?"

"Easily," said Eslane Ree. "We're scientists, not spies."

"And to involve ourselves in any such irregular transspecies dealings is completely unwise," said Ayana Sanoclaro.

"And for all we know the bugs are the bad guys and the bats are the good guys," said Septen Bolangyr. We'll be putting our noses into something we don't remotely understand. That doesn't feel very healthy to me."

"But can't you see-"

"Won't you realize-"

"If you'd only stop to consider-"

And so on until Wing-Marra, running out of patience at last, cut through the uproar to say, "I make it three in favor, three against. All right. I cast the tie-breaking vote. We go in with the Locrians. "

"No!" The word came from Eslane Ree and Ayana Sanoclaro in the same instant. "Impossible! Unthinkable!"

"And very stupid," said Bolangyr.

"Those who don't like it," Wing-Marra replied, "can place formal objections on file. We will take official notice and proceed as planned." To Eslane Ree he said, "This is a scientific mission, yes. But it's also an Erthuma spacesh!p, and all Erthuma ships have the responsibility of protecting Erthuma interests in space, which sometimes involves monitoring the activities of the other five stargoing species. That's what we're supposed to do, and that's what we're going to do. Clear? Good. Murry-Balff, I want to talk to you about what instruments we're going to use to scan the Crotonite lunar base. Sanoclaro, put together a Crotonite master psychological profile for me. I need to know what makes those bats tick. You have twenty minutes. Eslane Ree, park us around that second planet's moon and compute a landing orbit that'll put our groundship down somewhere in the neighborhood of the Crotonite base. Bolangyr, run the usual maintenance checks on all extravehicular-activity equipment. I think that's all for now. " He paused a moment. "No. There's one thing more. Hyath, go down below and tell the snake xcuse me, the Naxians-what we've just decided. Ask one of them to volunteer for the landing party.

"And me?" Mikoil Karpov asked.

Wing-Marra realized that he had provided an assignment for everyone except Biochemistry. But he couldn't see any immediate role for Karpov in any of this.

Then, with a pang, the captain remembered that they had all come to this obscure comer of the galaxy for a reason that had nothing to do with Locrians or Crotonites or galactic power politics. For a long sad moment he stared at the glowing screen of the spectrometer. Neglected though it was, it was still flashing bright-hued reports from the nearby molecular cloud. Tbrough Wing-Marra's mind went roiling visions of esoteric hydrocarbons, life-giving amino acids, complex polyvalents of a thousand kinds, stirring about tantalizingly in that mysterious ocean of intricate gases that lay just beyond his reach. He sighed.

"You keep an eye on the spectrometer screen," he told Karpov. "There's no telling what sort of significant stuff is going to turn up inside that cloud. And we aren't going to stop the whole mission dead in its tracks while we deal with this distraction. Not if I can help it. Okay? Okay. Adjourned."

They set up their camp in the long shadow of the great mountains, fifty kilometers from the Crotonite moon base: close enough so that the curvature of the lunar surface would not interfere with Murry-Balff's instruments, but not so close that the Crotonites would come running right over to put up a fuss.

The first thing Wing-Marra did was to send out an all-frequencies neutrino-wave announcement telling the entire galaxy that a joint Erthuma-Naxian-Locrian expedition had landed to investigate certain "anomalies" on a moon of the second planet of an unclaimed main-sequence star in the W49 nebula, where a Crotonite exploration team appeared to be already at work.

Murry-Balff said quizzically, "Sir, is that such a- good idea? The Crotonites can't fail to pick that message up. Should we really be letting them know we're here?"

"They already know we're here," Wing-Marra said, .amused. "Do you think we can put a groundship down right in their backyard without their noticing? What the message does is tell everyone else that we're here. In case the Crotonites have any idea of defending their turf against intruders. If we were to attempt a secret landing, they might feel it was safe to respond with an immediate lethal attack. "

"Against a transspecies ship? But that would be an act of war!" Murry-Balff exclaimed.

"Yes, it would. That's why I want to make it difficult for them to proceed with it. Most of us operate under the sane and reasonable assumption that one species will never attack another, but I suspect the Crotonites may operate under the assumption that they shouldn't attack another species unless they think they can get away with it. If everybody for fifty thousand light-years around knows we've landed here, the Crotonites are less likely to undertake military action against us. Or so I hope."

In fact he had no real idea how the Crotonites were likely to react to anything, but he was prepared for the worst. The psychological profile of them that Ayana Sanoclaro had drawn up for him was profoundly disturbing in that regard.

Of the five senior races of the galaxy, the Crotonites were the least predictable and, potentially at least, the most dangerous. Only their preference for. worlds with thick atmospheres heavily laced with ammonia and hydrogen cyanide, evidently, is what had kept them out of serious conflict with the other races. The worlds they inhabited were unendurable to the other species; the worlds they coveted were worlds that none of the others would want.

What set them apart from the other intelligent species of the galaxy, possibly even more than their metabolic differences, was the fact that they were the only one that had wings. Locrians and Erthumoi walked upright; Naxians were wrigglers; Cephallonians, aquatic; the ponderous Samians, when they deigned to move at all, rolled. But Crotonites were fliers.

On their home worlds they lived primarily airborne lives, moving slowly but with a strange grace through the heavy atmosphere, swooping and rising, rising and swooping. Lesser winged creatures were their food, caught always while in flight. They had no cities, only small transient settlements fashioned of twisted fiber, which they abandoned after only short periods of occupation. How they had ever attained the technological capacity to achieve interstellar travel was hard for Erthumoi to understand; but, then, it was hard for Erthumoi to see how any of the Five Races, except perhaps the Locrians, had managed to cross that difficult-to-attain threshold. Yet they all had, where thousands of other intelligent species had not. Some force had driven them, often against all biological and mechanical probability, to reach outward not only to their neighboring worlds but to the stars themselves.

Could it be, Wing-Marra wondered, that the force that had impelled the Crotonites outward was hate?

Certainly they manifested plenty of that in their dealings with the other races. They scarcely troubled to conceal their contempt for beings who had no wings. "Groundcrawlers," they called them or "mud-lickers" or "land-slugs. " So great was their disdain for all things wingless that they could not bear even to eat the meat of the unwinged, predatory carnivores though they were: It was shameful, they explained, to incorporate the flesh of landslugs into their own high-soaring bodies.

Once they had learned that various sorts of wingless mud-lickers had found a way of traveling between the stars, therefore, the Crotonites must have felt that they too would have to go forth into that vast darkness. And they had not rested until they also had solved the mysteries of hyperspace travel.

Once they did enter the community of starfaring races, they accepted the presence of those who already roamed the galaxy, because they had no choice about it. There was no way for them to maintain absolute isolation from the rest. Interstellar commerce requires a certain amount of contact with alien creatures, and it is economically suicidal to let racial prejudices get in the way of that. But they made it plain that they did no more than tolerate any of the others, and that in fact what they felt for them was loathing and enmity.

They did not, of course, carry those feelings to the extent of actual warfare. If there ever had been any such thing as interstellar warfare, it had gone out of fashion long before the first Erthurna starfarers had come upon the scene. One reason for that was the logistical difficulty of waging war on a galactic scale, even with hyperdriveequipped vessels. Another was that in a galaxy of effectively infinite size there was very little motive for serious territorial disputes among six intelligent life-forms whose environmental requirements were all mutually incompatible. But the main reason, probably, why the Crotonites never acted upon their hostility toward the wingless was that they knew the wingless would not permit war to break out. Nothing was apt to draw the separate races together more swiftly than any sort of conflict that might lead to war. War was an expensive nuisance; war was a messy disruption; war simply could not be allowed. The Crotonites probably knew that they would be annihilated at once by a united all-species force if they ever gave vent to their deepest emotions, and that helped to keep the galactic peace.

Instead they cheated wherever they could, they swindled, they behaved toward the wingless in all ways as though matters of morality were unimportant. The wingless in turn bore little love for them. Erdiumoi, who had their own not very -complimentary nicknames for each of the other galactic races, called the Crotonites "bats," or sometimes even "devils." And now Wing-Marra found himself camped fifty kilometers from a nest of them.

"This moon can't have been airless very long," Linga Hyath was saying.

"Probably it was just as habitable as its primary world, once upon a time."

"You think so?" Wing-Marra said.

They stood, spacesuit-clad, arrayed in a semicircle around Murry-Balff as he bent over the bank of instruments that he had set up on the bed of the dry sea. There were eight in the group: Wing-Marra, Hyath, Sanoclaro, Murry-Balff, Eslane Ree, the Naxian Blue Sphere, and two of the Locrians. Septen Bolangyr, Mikoil Karpov, and Rosy Tetrahedron had remained behind on the Achilles.

Hyath indicated the towering mountain range that loomed behind them. "Those are very big mountains," she said. "The sort you'd expect to find on a moon like this. But look at the way they've been worn down. For most of their existence they've been subjected to wind and rain and the other geological forces of a living world. But of course an atmosphere will wander off into space if a world's not big enough to hold it by gravitational force and if it's warm enough so that the atmospheric molecules can move faster than the local escape velocity. There was a time when this place must have had an atmosphere pretty much like its primary's, I'd guess-these two are really a double-planet system, most Rely with similar outgassing history-but the moon, large though it is, was too small, and too warm, to keep its air. Little by little the entire atmosphere was able to break free of the gravitational field here and escape. And eventually there was none left at all. "

"How long ago did that happen, would you say?" Eslane Ree asked.

"Oh, quite recently, quite recently indeed," said Hyath "Within the last two or three hundred million years, is my top-of-the-head answer. " Eslane Ree chuckled. "Oh. Only two or three hundred million years ago! That's your idea of quite recently?"

"Surely you understand that on the geological time scale that's only-"

"Hold it," Wing-Marra said. "I think Murry-Balff's got something."

The Communications had been leaning forward over his control panel, muttering to himself, shaking his head, tapping in data setups, wiping them out, tapping new ones in. Suddenly the board was alive with flashing lights.

"Okay," Murry-Balff said. "I think we have data capture."

Wing-Marra peered close. The readout was analog, but he could make nothing of the patterns he saw.

"What I've done," said Murry-Balff, "has been to plot light-wave deviation first. That's this information here. Assuming there's a zone of significant surface mass in that supposedly empty zone, it ought to have at least some relativistic effects on photons traveling through its vicinity, regardless of the visual data corruption that the Crotonites are managing to throw up around it. Okay. There it is." He pointed to a pattern in green and red at the side of his panel. It meant nothing at all to Wing-Marra. Murry-Balff said, "It's next to imperceptible, but that's what you'd expect of any sort of mass smaller than a continent, anyway. But the fact is that it isn't imperceptible. What I'm picking up is the bending I expected, right here-and here-4hat's an inferred computation of the required size of whatever's causing the perturbation. Those are the boundaries of the concealed object, see?"

"Show me that again," Wing-Marra said.

Murry-Balff made a quick gesture with his light pen.

"But that's enormous!" said Wing-Marra. "It's the size of a small city!"

"That's right. Not such a small one, either. The area is umm.. sixty-four square kilometers, plus or minus four. Now, we get the sonar in there and we try to see whether it'll penetrate the Crotonite data shield; and we discover that we can, more or less, although the perimeter data is likewise corrupt and has to be factored for a standard distortion deviation, which the little brain here in this box has been kind enough to work out for me. We bounce the sound waves through the invisibility shield, and luckily for us, the shield doesn't screen them out once we're inside and so far as I can tell does not corrupt our data, but returns us a clean readout. Which gives us the horizon profile of the concealed object."

"Where?"

"Here. You see? These ups, these downs. The skyline, so to speak, of the hidden city. And the mean elevation is-well, rooftop level, I make out to be eleven and one half meters, with a deviation of-umm-the tallest building is, let's say, twenty-one and one half meters, but there aren't many of those, and most of the others are, well, single-story structures-"

"Structures?" Ayana Sanoclaro said. "You've got actual buildings showing on that screen?"

The two Locrians were murmuring now in their own harsh, clicking language. The Naxian, agitated, was rapidly thrusting its little flipper-limbs forth and retracting diem.

"Didn't you hear me?" Murry-Balff said. "There's a city under the Crotonite screen. Now that I'm past their corruption line, I'll have the whole thing mapped out for you in less than fifteen minutes. "

"A city?" Sanoclaro said in wonder. "The Crotonites have built a city on this airless moon? Under some sort of dome, do you mean?"

Murry-Balff looked up at her. "Did I say it was a Crotonite city? Do the Crotonites even build cities? There's no dome that I can see, at least not an actual physical one, though of course all I'm getting is shadow images, and it's possible that a dome viewed edge-on might somehow not show up on my screen. I can check that out from another angle. But you can see the building profiles, can't you?" He waved his hands grandly over the panel, which was still entirely incomprehensible to Wing-Marra. "There's nothing Crotonite-looking here. Look, these are streets and avenues. Crotonites don't ordinarily have streets and avenues, do they? And those are solid, rounded structures with vaulted roofs. I don't have the foggiest idea what they are, but Crotonite they aren't."

"But who-?" Sanoclaro demanded, gesturing bewdderedly. "It isn't one of ours, or we'd have had records of a landing here. It can't be Locrian. The Cephallonians would hardly build a settlement on a world that doesn't have a drop of water. The Samians-the Naxians-"

"Why does it have to be a city belonging to any of the Six Races?" Wing-Marra asked suddenly.

Everyone stared at him.

"What are you saying?" asked Eslane Ree. "That there's a seventh interstellar race somewhere that nobody knows about yet?"

"I don't know," Wing-Marra told her. "Right now all I can do is ask questions, not answer them." To Hyath he said, "You believe that this place once was as habitable as its companion planet, but that it's been airless like this for-how long? Three hundred million years?"

"Plus or minus a hundred million," said Hyath.

"Same difference." He closed his eyes a moment. Then, turning to the Locrians, he said, "You people were the first of the Six Races to achieve star travel, right? How long ago was that?"

"It was in the Eighteenth Era," one of the Locrians began.

"Translate that into Galactic Standard Years. Please."

After a moment the Locrian said, "You would think of it as approximately three hundred fifteen thousand years before the present time."

Wing-Marra nodded. By Linga Hyath's geological way of reckoning things, that was only a heartbeat ago. He said, "And when you first got out into interstellar space, did you encounter any other starfaring races then, older races that are extinct now?"

"No," said the Locrian. "We did, of course, come upon the ruins of ancient civilizations which perhaps had been galactic in nature, though we do not believe that they were. But of living galactic races-no, no, we were the first of our epoch. And perhaps the first in the history of this galaxy."

"I'm not so sure of that," said Wing-Marra, half to himselL

His mind was racing. Knowledge he had not called upon in hundreds of years came bubbling now out of its deep hiding place.

In the second cycle of his life, flushed with the new youth of his first rejuvenation, he had turned his attention toward the remote past with much the same intensity as he had much later taken up organic chemistry.

Archaeology then had been the center of his energies, and for decades he had pored backward into the yesterdays of his species, digging into the few hundred years of history that his native world of Hesperia could provide, then onward, deeper, to Earth, the mother world of all Erthumoi, where antiquity was measured in hundreds of centuries: Chichen ItzA, Pompeii, Babylon, Troy, Luxor, Lascaux. But even that had not satisfied his hunger for antiquity, for Earth was a young world as galactic worlds went, and the Erthumoi a very young race: The mother planet offered no more than thirty thousand or forty thousand years of past that had the richness and complexity he sought, and beyond that lay nothing but stray scraps of bone, scatterings of stone tools, the charred ashes of ancient hearths.

So he had gone out into the galaxy again, digging on worlds beyond the Erthuma sphere. At least ten thousand of the worlds of the galaxy had evolved intelligent lifeforms. Only a relative handful of those had gone on to develop technological civilizations, and some of those were extinct: dead by their own hands, so it would appear. Of the survivors, only five, before the Erthumoi, had reached the level of interstellar travel. It was not generally thought that any of the extinct races had succeeded in traveling beyond their own solar systems. A widely held theory argued that there was a critical technological threshold that every race had to pass; the ability to achieve self-destruction invariably came sooner than the ability to attain interstellar flight, and only those races able to master their own self-destructive impulses would last long enough to master the mysteries of hyperspace travel. Many had not.

Wing-Marra had probed the ruins of dead alien civilizations in a dozen different star systems. But they too were disappointing to someone seeking vivid and immediate insight into the look and texture of the distant past. Even in the best preserved of them, not much had withstood the inroads of time: a faint line of stone foundations here, an empty burial vault there, some shattered walls, a battered fragment or two of strange jewelry, perhaps a bit of some unfamiliar and unrecognizable fossil, and not much more. That was all that remained. The youngest of those lost civilizations was one hundred thousand Galactic Standard Years old, according to his dating instruments; the oldest was five times as ancient as that. Mere traces, outlines in the sand.

But now-on a world where no one could have lived for hundreds of millions of years-

A city? A complete city, with a discernible street plan and buildings still so intact, after whole geological eras, that roofs still remained and the number of stories could be counted? No, that was archaeological nonsense, WingMarra thought. Whatever lay out there on that dead plain, it could not possibly be a settlement that went back to a time when this world still had air and water and vegetation. But what, then? Perhaps, in the stillness and void of this lifeless moon, the familiar forces of erosion would not operate as they did elsewhere, and whatever was built here would remain through all the ages, undecayed. Why would anyone bother, though, to build a fair-sized city on so absolutely inhospitable a place as this world had become once its atmosphere had fled? And who would have done it? Norte of the Five Races, that seemed certain. And surely not Erthumoi.

A seventh galactic race, unknown to all the others?

It had to be.

It could not be.

This makes no sense, Wing-Marra thought. None whatsoever.

"What are you thinking?" Sanoclaro asked.

"A lot of things," said Wing-Marra. "But I don't have enough information. Do you know what we need to do now? We need to get into our buggies and ride over across there to take a close look at whatever it is that the Crotonites don't want us to see."

It was, of course, an outrageous thing to be doing. The ground vehicles were equipped with weaponry, and both Wing-Marra and Murry-Balff were carrying hand-model blasters, which were not uncommon items of male ornamental dress on their home world. The Locrians, too, were armed. But in all the cycles of his life Wing-Marra had never once had occasion to use his blaster against another living creature, and he doubted that Murry-Balff had either. As for using it against a member of one of the other galactic races-no, no, it was unthinkable for a member of one race to injure a member of another.

He was counting on the fact that the Crotonites were likely to feel the same way.

Besides, this solar system was unclaimed. If the Crotonites had taken the trouble to claim it, they could have closed both the second planet and its moon to all other races, and backed that up, if necessary, by force. But they had filed no claim. Whether they had chosen that course for some unfathomable sneaky Crotonite reason or simply because they had been too confident that no other race would find this place was something Wing-Marra did not know. Either way, as things stood, they had no legal right to bar anyone else from landing here.

They could, naturally, keep trespassers from entering any base they had established themselves. But Wing-Marra had no intention of going anywhere near the Crotonite base. All he wanted to inspect was that big empty place out on the bed of the vanished lunar sea. That was no Crotonite base, was it? That was simply an empty place. How could they stop him from driving right up to it? From peering in? From entering it, if he could? They would have to admit that there was something there, after all, before they could keep him from trying to look at it.

At first, it seemed as though the Locrians would not buy any of his reasoning and were going to refuse to accompany him into the plain. They were afraid of some violation of Crotonite territorial rights that would lead to big political trouble. The Naxian, too, was uneasy about going along. Naxians, because of their keen intuitive sense of what might be going on in any organism's mind, were usually confident of their ability to handle themselves in all sorts of bothersome situations. But Blue Sphere, like the Locrians, indicated that it-she would just as soon stay away from the Crotonite outpost.

Wing-Marra was unhappy about that. He wanted the Locrians and the Naxian along for a show of solidaritythe Crotonites were less likely to commit some hostile act if they saw that they'd be stiffing up trouble with three of the Six Races at once-and also he valued Naxian intuition and Locrian cold-blooded intellectuality. But they would not give in.

"Very well," Wing-Marra said finally. "We'll just have to go without you, I guess."

Which broke the impasse, for the Locrians did not trust their Erthuma partners sufficiently to want them to get first look at the enigma on the plain without them, and Blue Sphere, although it-she plainly suspected that Wing-Marra was bluffing, apparently did not want to take the risk that he was crazy enough to mean what he said. So in the end they all went: a tri-species expedition, setting out in two ground vehicles across the hard flat limestone floor of the ancient dry sea.

They were still twenty kilometers or so from the zone of mystery when Eslane Ree pointed out a Crotonite landcrawler coming up on their left.

"Everyone into defensive mode," Wing-Marra ordered. "All weaponry armed and ready, but don't get overanxious. Let's just see what they do."

What the Crotonites did was to swing into a path parallel to theirs at a distance of perhaps half a kilometer, and ride alongside them. A little while later, a second Crotonite vehicle took up the same escort position on the right. Then a third appeared, hanging back to the rear. All dime maintained constant distances from the Erthuma vehicles as they traveled over the plain.

"The bats watch us, and we watch the bats," WingMarra said. "And neither side makes the first move. All right. We wait and see, and so do they. How far are we from the edge of the zone, Murry-Blaff?"

"Seven hundred meters."

"Well, we'll have some answers pretty soon."

"Here," MurTy-Balff said. "This is it."

Wing-Marra signaled and the caravan came to a halt. They seemed to be in the middle of nowhere. Behind diem, far behind, lay the mountains and their camp, and some distance off to the soudi the Crotonite camp. Ahead of them, stretching out almost endlessly, was the bright, chalky, almost featureless plain that once had been the floor of a prehistoric ocean. The green second world, hanging overhead, seemed closer than ever, a massive, looming weight; and its brilliant light cast an eerie, chilling glow.

Right in front of us, Wing-Marra thought, is a city that may be half a billion years old. And we can't see a damned thing.

"Here come the Crotonites," Eslane Ree said.

"Yes. I'm aware of them. Let's get out and sniff around a little. "

He was the first out of the vehicle. After a moment, one of the Locrians jumped out also, and then the other. Sanoclaro and Eslane Ree followed.

Murry-Balff remained with his instruments. Blue Sphere, looking fidgety and troubled, stayed in the vehicle also. Wing-Marra beckoned to it-her to get out. Murry-Balff could do his work from the vehicle, if he wanted to, but Wing-Marra needed the Naxian by his side.

He took a few steps forward, wondering if he would feel resistance. But there was nothing. Nothing at all.

"Am I near it?" he asked.

"Another ten meters," Murry-Balff replied. "But the Crotonites--

"Yes. I know."

From the right, the left, the rear, the three Crotonite land-crawlers came zeroing in, and pulled up in an open are around the two Erthuma vehicles. Wing-Marra, though he knew the gesture was preposterous, let his hand rest lightly on the blaster strapped to the side of his spacesuit. God help us all, he told himself, if it comes down to stuff like that. But he felt he had at least to make the gesture.

The Crotonites were out of their land-crawlers, now, six of them, approaching him in the peculiarly dismaying waddling shuffle that they employed when they were forced to walk on the surface of a world. Seen close up, they were less frightful looking than when flying like devils through the air, because their huge wings were furled and swaddled within their pressure suits. That way, they appeared as short, plump, almost comical little beings, standing no more than waist high to an Erthuma. But they were, Wing-Marra thought, pretty evil looking all the same. The great ungainly bulk of the folded wings behind them provided an ominous reminder of their true forms, and their long sharp-featured heads, crested and bony chinned, had a harsh, repellent, monstrous look.

"Turn on the simultrans," Wing-Marra said to MurryBalff.

The Crotonites, he knew, would never deign to speak Erthumat. And he knew only seven words in Crotoni, four of them obscene and the others profane.

"Who is the leader here?" asked the shortest and fiercestlooking of the Crotonites, one with diabolical yellow eyes streaked with bands of red.

Wing-Marra raised his hand. "I am. Captain Hayn WingMarra of the Erthuma research vessel Achilles."

"I am Hiuptis," said the Crotonite. "What are you doing here, Captain Wing-Marra?"

"Why, we've been out for a drive. And now we're taking a little walk."

"I mean what are you doing in this solar system."

"Carrying out chemical research. We're studying the molecular cloud nearby."

"And does the molecular cloud extend to the surface of this moon?"

"Not at all. But while we were in orbit up there we ran into some old friends from Locria, who suggested that we all come down here for a little rest and relaxation."

"Indeed," said the Crotonite coldly. "This moon is an extremely relaxing place. But I suggest that you enjoy yourselves elsewhere. If you continue in the direction you are traveling, you will very shortly be trespassing on a research center established by and operated for the exclusive use of the Galactic Sphere of Crotonis."

"Will we?" Wing-Marra said. "A research center, you say? Where? I don't see anything here at all." He took a deep breath and began to move forward, indicating with a small movement of his hand that the others should come with him. "It's absolutely empty out here, so far as I can tell. "

Murry-Balff said softly, "You're within two meters of the shield perimeter now, sir."

"Yes. I know."

Wing-Marra took another step.

The Crotomtes began to look extremely agitated. 1"heir bright, beady eyes glearned and flickered, and they shifted their weight awkwardly from one to the other of their short, bhVRe legs. Wing-Marra imagined that they would be flapping their wings, too, if their wings were not pinioned within their pressure suits. As he walked forward, the Crotonites hopped along beside him, keeping pace.

"One meter, sir," Murry-Balff said.

Wing-Marra nodded and stepped across the invisible line.

It was like walking through a wall. Inside, everything was different. He was standing in a kind of antechamber, an open space that curved'off to either side at a wide angle. Behind him was the barren plain, still visible, and straight ahead of him, perhaps fifty meters ahead, lay a zone of absolute blackness, so dense and dark that it could well have been the outer boundary of the universe. The space between the invisible wall to his rear and the blackness ahead formed the antechamber, which was brightly lit by drifting clusters of glowfloats and cluttered everywhere with alien-looking instruments. It was full of Crotonites, too, who were staring at him with a look on their demonic bony faces that was surely the Crotonite equivalent of the most extreme astonishment.

Murry-Balff, still monitoring everything from the vehicle, said, "There's a second shielded zone within the first one, sir. "

"I'm looking right at it. It's black as the pit."

"It's totally light absorbent. But the sonar goes through. The city starts just on the other side."

The Crotonite who called itself Hiuptis tapped WingMarra urgently on his thigh. "Now do you see, Captain? Plainly this is a research zone, and delicate observations are in progress."

"Fascinating," said Wing-Marra. "I never would have believed it. "

"You concede that we are carrying on research here?"

"Yes. Yes, of course you are. That's plain to see."

"Then I call upon you to cease this trespass at once!"

"Ah, but we're not trespassing, are we?" Wing-Marra said lightly. "We're only visiting. It's a purely social thing. This is such a forlorn dead place, this moon. It's good to have the company of one's fellow creatures for a little while in a place like this. And as long as we're here, you really don't mind if we look around a bit, do you? What sort of research did you say you were doing, by the way? I don't seem to recall."

Hiuptis turned to the Locrians. " Ship-Commander! " the Crotonite cried sharply. "Will you be a party to this detestable intrusion also? I warn you that you will thereby involve the Galactic Sphere of Locria in the culpability, and our inevitable demand for reparations will extend to your sphere as well as that of Erthuma. You have been warned. "

"We take note of the warning," said one of the Locrians solemnly. "To which we reply that we are here only because we wish to pay our respects to the representatives of the Galactic Sphere of Crotonis, now that we have become aware that you too are present in this unknown and unclaimed solar system where both we and the Erthumoi have separately been carrying out research programs of our own."

The Locrian's emphasis on unclaimed was subtle but unmistakable. Hiuptis made a sputtering sound. It was shifting from foot to foot again, so quickly that it seemed almost to be hopping.

Wing-Marra glanced around. The Crotonites within the research station were unarmed, but the six who had come out to intercept the Erthuma vehicles carried blasters. He wondered what the chance was that they would use them if he continued to press forward. Certainly Hiuptis seemed furious, but so far the only threat it had made was that there would be a demand for reparations. Did that mean the Crotonites were ruling out any kind of attempt to end the intrusion by force? Or was Hiuptis merely trying to lull him with some slippery Crotonite sleight of tongue?

He looked toward Blue Sphere. The Naxian seemed to be aware of what Wing-Marra needed to know. It-she signaled relative calm: The Crotonites were angry, were, in fact, fuming mad, but there seemed to be no immediate danger of actual violence.

Of course, even Naxians weren't infallible. But WingMarra decided to risk it.

He began to move forward again, toward the strange zone of blackness that lay before him.

Hiuptis and the other five blaster-equipped Crotonites hopped frantically along at his side. "Captain Wing-Marra! Captain Wing-Marra! Captain Wing-Marra! " Hiuptis cried, again and again, in increasingly excited tones.

The other Crotonites, those who had been operating the myriad scanning devices that were aimed toward the wall of darkness, were staring at him, frozen with astonishment.

"Do you mean to go in there?" Hiuptis asked. "Surely not! Surely not, Captain Wing-Marra!"

Wing-Marra turned toward his Naxian again. Blue Sphere looked troubled now.

They are afraid, it-she told Wing-Marra with a silent gesture. They are angry that you are in here where they do not want you to go, but they are afraid, also, of what may happen if you go in there. It is for your sake that they are afraid.

"MurTy-Balfff' Wing-Marra said. "Do you have any reading on what's going on on the other side of the inner screen? Do you pick up the presence of any Crotonites over there?"

"I don't, sir, no. But that doesn't mean there aren't any, only that the sonar doesn't-"

"Right," Wing-Marra said. He looked toward the Locrians. "What about you?

Can you try to see through that darkness and tell me what's behind there?"

The Locrians, after a moment's hesitation, unveiled their inner eyes, and turned their piercing three-dimensional vision toward the black void ahead. "Buildings," reported one of the Locrians, its voice sounding oddly strangled.

"Buildings, yes," said the other. "Streets. A whole city is there."

"No Crotonites?"

"No living thing at all," the first Locrian said. "It is very quiet in there. It is extremely still. "

"Fine," Wing-Marra said. "I'll take a look."

"Captain!" Esiane Ree cried, in horror. "No!"

"Captain Wing-Marra! " said Hiuptis, practically squawking with rage and frustration. "I forbid-I utterly forbid-"

"Excuse me," Wing-Marra said. "I'll be right back, I promise you."

Quickly, before he could change his mind, he stepped into the zone of darkness.

The first thing he noticed on the far side was that he was still alive. He had been prepared to die-eleven cycles might well be quite enough, he had often thought-but that had not happened.

The second bit of information that came to him was the amber glow on the arm-monitor of his suit that told him he was now in the presence of an atmosphere. An oxygenbased atmosphere, at that. He could probably take his spacesuit off altogether in here, though he did not intend to. This place was like a world unto itself, sealed off within the screens that shielded it. Perhaps the atmosphere in here was the one the city had had when this moon was still alive.

Then, as his vision adapted to the low light level within the inner shield, he saw the city.

It was stunning beyond his comprehension. Low buildings, yes-Murry-Balff's readouts had been right about that. In a perfect state of preservation, absolutely new looking, and so totally strange in their architecture that he felt as though he had wandered into a land of dreams. Everything seemed to melt and flow: domes became parapets, walls became balconies, windows turned to arches. All was fluid, and yet everything was fixed, solid, eternal.

Unfamiliar colors teased his eyes. He could almost have believed that he was seeing in some far comer of the spectrum, that these were the hues beyond violet, or perhaps the ones below red.

Wonderstruck, he moved forward, down a narrow street that seemed to widen invitingly as he entered it.

The movement, he realized, was an illusion. Nothing moved here. All was in stasis: timeless, silent, free from any sort of decay. There was no dust. There were no cracks in the walls. This was a city outside time, shielded against all harm. No tectonic movement within the depths of this moon had left its mark on these flawless structures. No meteors had come plunging through the airless sky to crash through these roofs. No spider had spun here. Moth and rust were strangers here. An eternity and a half might have passed since the builders of this place had taken their leave of it, but nothing about it had changed.

How was that possible? What spell of enchantment kept this place invulnerable against the tooth of time?

He went close, peering through windows that seemed opaque and translucent at the same time. There were objects in the buildings: artifacts, mechanisms. He saw things on shelves that baffled and awed and astounded him. Wing-Marra began to tremble. Should he go in? No, he thought. Not now. Not yet. He might be pushing his luck too far. Who knew what traps awaited him in there, to guard those ancient treasures against intruders? And yet, to think that all the wonders of an unknown technology were just on the far side of those shimmering walls-

He was choking with amazement. There was no place to compare with this in all the galaxy.

He touched a wall. It seemed to give slightly against the pressure of his fingertips. And then suddenly the sky above him was ablaze with the whirling snakes of the Kekule ring. The fiery vision of a gigantic organic molecule danced before him. It was none that he had ever seen or even imagined before; immense, bewilderingly intricate, joined in a thousand thousand places, holding forth the possibility of infinite complexity. He stared into it and it was like staring into a new universe. After a time he let go of the wall and took a few tottering steps backward.

The vision faded at once and was gone.

But the impact, lingering, was overwhelming. Wing-Marra's mind throbbed. He had to get away. He needed to come to terms with what he had seen. He could not bear to remain in this place any longer.

He swung about and ran through the silent streets toward the blackness, and burst through it, and stumbled out into the antechamber. The bright lights dazzled him painfully and he shrank away from them, covering his face for a moment, closing his eyes. When he felt able to open them again, he saw them all staring at him in wonder, Crotonites, Locrians, his own people, all of them appalled, all of them aghast.

"You are alive?" Hiuptis whispered.

"Alive, yes. How long was I in there?"

Eslane Ree said, "A minute or so. No more."

"It seemed like- years."

"What was in there?" Ayana Sanoclaro asked.

Wing-Marra gestured. "Go in and see for yourself."

"Are you serious?"

"Go in!" he cried. "All of you! You've never imagined anything like that!

I wasn't hurt-why should you be?" He looked down at the Crotonite commander. "You mean to say that you never went in there, not once, not any of you?"

"No," Hiuptis murmured. "Never. We thought it was too dangerous. We only scanned it from outside, and nothing more. The shields-we were not sure if they were lethal. Finally we risked a penetration of the outer one. But the other-the other-"

"So you didn't put the shields up yourselves?"

The Crotonite made a gesture of negation.

"No," Wing-Marra said. "Naturally you didn't. Neither the invisibility shield nor the decay-proof shield inside it. We couldn't figure out how you had done it, and of course you hadn't done it. You don't have the technology for that. Nobody in the galaxy does. You just stumbled on the whole thing, and you've been dancing around the edges of it. Well, go on in now! All of you! Go and see! My God, there are miracles in there! And who can even guess how old it all is? Fifty million years? A billion? It can sit like that forever right to the end of time."

"Captain-" It was Linga Hyath. "Captain, you're getting too excited. "

"Damned right I am!" Wing-Marra cried. "Go in there and see! Go in, will you? See for yourselves!"

Afterward, when everyone had come stumbling out, hushed and dazed and dumbfounded, a strained silence fell. The vastness of the wonders that they had seen seemed to have overcome them all.

Only the Locrians appeared able to come to terms immediately with that grand and staggering experience. To Wing-Marra's amazement they joined hands and pranced about in a weird, jubilant dance, rubbing their antennae together as they cavorted. No doubt they were already counting the profits that could be mined from the hoard of treasure beyond the shield.

It was then that Hiuptis came to Wing-Marra and said, in a dark, cold tone the Erthuma had not heard from it before, "You wingless ones will leave our research center now, and you will not return. You will obey without further discussion."

There was insistence in Hiuptis's crackling voice and menace and something else; the implication, perhaps, that everyone there needed a time to retreat and digest the meaning of the discovery. But mainly there was menace and insistence. Wing-Marra suspected that there might be real violence, despite all taboos, if they tried to remain any longer; and Blue Sphere backed up his suspicions with the blunt warning that the Crotonites were reaching a point of exasperation that might prove explosive.

"Don't worry," Wing-Marra told Hiuptis. "We're going to go. You can have the place to yourselves again."

The Locrians halted their strange dance instantly. One of them turned to Wing-Marra in amazement, its great eye gleaming, and said, "But our agreement-I"

Wing-Marra met its glare with one of his own. "We can discuss that later. I'm calling for a withdrawal. I'm not ready to take any further steps here. You can do as you please.''

"Leaving this find to them?" the Locrian said, astounded. "Incredible! You actually mean to withdraw and let them have- "

"For the time being," said Wing-Marra. "Only for the time being."

The Locrian rose to its full height and waved its forelimbs furiously in protest. But Wing-Marra, turning quickly away, began to walk toward the perimeter of the outer screen, toward the ground vehicles waiting just outside it.

Sanoclaro came up beside him. "Are you serious? You're really just going to pull out now?"

He whirled to face her. "What do you think I'm going to do? Start a war with Crotonis over it? These Crotonites are half crazy with confusion and rage and greed and outraged pride and God knows what other emotions, all of them dangerous. They're right at the point where they'll kill to get us out of here, now. Do you want to see if they will?"

"But to allow them sole possession of such a find-

"For the moment," said Wing-Marra. "Only for the moment. They're in possession, but they don't have ownership. Nobody does. They discovered it, sure. But they didn't claim it, which they probably thought was very clever. Then the Locrians found out about it and got us involved. I went in on my own hook, which the Crotonites hadn't dared to do, and discovered that it's accessible and full of incredible things. You understand this sort of stuffYou can see how muddled the claim is by this time. Let higher authorities figure it out now. The only thing that's certain is that nothing's ever going to be the same again in this galaxy."

"But what do you think the city is?" Sanoclaro asked.

"Something left behind by a race greater than any of the Six," said

Wing-Marra quietly. "That's all I- know. I couldn't begin to guess who they were. Or are."

"Are? But you said the site might be a billion years old! "

"It might, yes. Or a million. And its builders might have become extinct before there was vertebrate life on Earth. Or they might still be out there somewhere, hidden away in some unexplored arm of the galaxy, or in some other galaxy entirely. Maybe we'll stumble upon them. Or maybe they'll come back from wherever they are and pay us a visit. Or maybe they'll never be heard from again. In any case, the damage is done."

"Me damage."

"There's a city full of a superior alien technology sitting here. Now that we know what to look for, we may find that there are fifty more invisible cities just like it stashed around the galaxy too, or five hundred, full of the most astounding gadgets anyone has ever dreamed of. You can bet that all that technology, if anybody can figure out what to use it for, is going to destablize the equilibrium among the Six Races that keeps this galaxy peaceful. Or worse: Suppose the builders themselves ever come back and de- cide to play with us--choosing sides among the Six Races, picking allies, making enemies, maybe looking for vassalscan you imagine what that will do?"

"Yes," said Sanoclaro quietly. "I can."

They reached the ground vehicle. Wing-Marra turned for one last look at the place where the city lay hidden.

He saw nothing. Nothing at all, only the bare bright expanse of the flat stark plain, and a few Crotonite groundcrawlers. He shook his head.

Everything will be different from now on, he thought. Nothing will ever be the same again.

"Let's get back to the ship," he said wearily. All his people stood waiting by the vehicles, each one of them seemingly lost in astonished recollection of the vision they had seen. "I need to put together some sort of a report," he said. "The whole Erthuma sphere will know about this place by tomorrow. The whole damned galaxy, I suppose. "

"And then?" Eslane Ree asked. "What will we do after that?"

"Who knows? That's not my concern right now. I've had enough excitement.

I've got other work to do, you know. I still want to see what sort of hydrocarbons are floating around in that molecular cloud. " He allowed his eyes to close, and the alien city sprang to life behind his lids, strange dreamlike buildings stretching on and on to the horizon, and every one of them laden with implements and devices of unknown and perhaps unknowable use. He saw the vision again, bearing promise of chemistries beyond any chemistry he had ever known. His whole being throbbed with the recollection of what he had seen and felt behind that wall of darkness. A magical place, he thought. A place of wonders. And, maybe, of terrors. Time would tell.

Yes, he thought, everything is going to be different now, all throughout the galaxy. And, he suspected, he, too, would never be quite the same again. After such a vision, how could he be?

He smiled. Eleven cycles old, and he could still feel a little shiver of wonder now and then. That wasn't so bad. Of course, it -took something pretty spectacular to get that kind of response out of him: a cloud thirty light-years wide loaded with complex organic molecules, say, or an alien city a billion years old. But he had lived eleven lifetimes, after all.

After eleven cycles he couldn't be expected to react in a. big way to anything ordinary. He had seen all the ordinary things before, too many times.

He shrugged. It would be interesting to stick around for another cycle or two, and see what was going to happen next.

"Okay," he said, beckoning them all to get back into the ground vehicles.

"I think we're finished here for the time being. Let's go."